Milt Gabler Papers ARC.0003
Library and Archives
Milt Gabler Papers
Bulk, 1938-1969
1928-2006, undated
ARC.0003
Library and Archives
7.59 Linear feet (5 records cartons, 2 oversize boxes)
The Milt Gabler Papers span the years 1928 to 2006, with the bulk of the material dating between 1938 and 1969. The collection’s primary focus is Gabler’s career as founder of Commodore Records and as an artists and repertoire (A & R) executive for Decca Records. The collection includes material related to the Commodore Music Shop and Gabler’s Commodore Records years; artist files for those under contract with Decca Records and including photocopies of artists' cards, package information memoranda, label copy, handwritten notes, lyrics, lists of recordings, royalty statements, correspondence, and record personnel sheets; lyrics and sheet music composed by Gabler, much of which is handwritten; and correspondence between the Commodore Music Shop and its customers, which illustrates the enthusiasm with which records released on the Commodore label were received by the public. Additionally, the collection includes some of Gabler’s personal files, including awards, clippings, interview and radio transcripts, and some promotional material, as well as printed and audiovisual material. The printed materials relate to jazz and early rock and roll and include periodicals, newspapers, programs, and sheet music. Audiovisual materials in the collection include 1/4-inch audiotapes. Viewed as a whole, the Milt Gabler Papers document Gabler’s influence on the popularity of swing-era jazz and early rock and roll, as well as his success as a record store owner, record producer, and songwriter.
Gabler, Milt, 1911-2001
Biographical Note
1926 Gabler’s father opens the Commodore Radio Corporation (later Commodore Music Shop)in New York.
1937 Gabler moves the Commodore Music Shop to 52nd Street.
1938 Founds Commodore Records label.
1939 Records Billie Holiday’s “Strange Fruit” for Commodore.
1940 Begins hosting weekly jam sessions at Jimmy Ryan’s on 52nd Street.
1941 Goes to work for Decca Records as an A&R man at the invitation of Decca co-founder Jack Kapp.
1954 Signs Bill Haley and the Comets to Decca.
1959 Commodore Music Shop closes.
1971 Retires from Decca.
1993 Inducted into the Rock and Roll Hall of Fame.
2001 July 20 Dies at age 90.
As owner of the Commodore Music Shop on New York’s 52nd Street, Milt Gabler was an important influence in the swing-era jazz scene. In 1938 he founded Commodore Records, which recorded such artists as Louis Armstrong, Eddie Condon, Louis Jordan, and Jelly Roll Morton. When Columbia Records refused to produce Billie Holiday’s controversial “Strange Fruit,” Gabler invited Holiday to record the song for Commodore, giving Commodore its first commercial success. Gabler joined Decca Records in 1941, becoming one of the most influential artists and repertoire (A & R) executives of the early rock and roll era. He is credited with convincing Bill Haley and His Comets to add a heavier backbeat to “Rock Around the Clock,” thus ushering in a completely new style of popular music. Over the course of a career spanning more than five decades, Gabler produced over 40 recordings that sold more than a million copies each.
Sources
Milt Gabler, interview by Oral History Research Office, Columbia University, 1959, transcript, Milt Gabler Collection, Library and Archives, Rock and Roll Hall of Fame and Museum.
"Milt Gabler Biography." Rock and Roll Hall of Fame and Museum. Accessed June 18, 2010. http://rockhall.com/inductees/milt-gabler/bio.
Scott Yanow. "Milt Gabler." All Music Guide. Accessed June 18, 2010. http://www.allmusic.com/artist/milt-gabler-p78396/biography.
Custodial History note
The Milt Gabler Papers were received by the Rock and Roll Hall of Fame Foundation, Inc. as a gift from Lee Gabler on February 10, 2005. The Rock and Roll Hall of Fame Foundation, Inc. transferred the collection to the Rock and Roll Hall of Fame and Museum, Inc. on March 31, 2011.
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research. Patrons must sign the Acknowledgment of Legal Responsibility and Privacy Rights statement on the Researcher Registration form before using this collection. Some of the audiovisual materials in the collection are on defunct media formats and, therefore, are RESTRICTED. Consult the Library and Archives staff in advance of your visit to ensure access to these materials is available.
Separated Materials
Some print and audiovisual materials have been transferred to the library collection. Please search for the “Milt Gabler Papers" in the library catalog for a list of donated titles. If you are unable to find what you are looking for, consult the Library and Archives staff to ensure these materials are available.
Armstrong, Louis, 1901-1971; Commodore Records; Decca Records (Firm); Gabler, Lee; Haley, Bill, 1925-1981; Hampton, Lionel; Holiday, Billie, 1915-1959; Ives, Burl, 1909-1995; Kaempfert, Bert; 1/4 inch audio tape; Jazz; Lyricists; Music stores; Newspapers; Periodicals; Record labels; Rock music; Sheet music; Sound recording executives and producers
- Series I: Business Files, 1934-2000, undated
  Scope and Contents
  Series I: Business Files includes unpublished papers related to Gabler’s career with the Commodore Music Shop, Commodore Records, and Decca Records, as well as his career as a songwriter/lyricist. The series is organized by subseries and then alphabetically by file title.
  - Subseries 1: Commodore Records, 1934-1956, 1978, 1987, undated
    Organized alphabetically by file title.
    - Clippings, Commodore Record Shop and Milt Gabler, 1940-1978 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Commodore master list, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Contracts and and master list for the Special Music Company, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence, 1934-1952 and undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - General Record Company copyright licenses, R120-R205, 1939-1941 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - General Record Company copyright licenses, R1280-R1700, 1939-1940 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - General Record Company copyright licenses, R1800-R4000 and correspondence, 1939-1949 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - General Record Company correspondence, Ringling Brothers & Barnum & Bailey Circus recordings, 1940-1942 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Ledger
      - 1956 (Box 1, Folder 9)
      - circa 1950s (Box 1, Folder 10-12)
      - undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Promotional materials, Commodore Music Shop, Jimmy Ryan’s, United Hot Clubs of America, The Friday Club, Stuyvesant Casino, 1944 and undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Session sheets (Box 1, Folder 15)
      - 1941-1943 (Box 1, Folder 15)
      - 1944 February-1944 March (Box 1, Folder 16)
      - 1944 April-1944 July (Box 1, Folder 17)
      - 1944 September-1945 October (Box 1, Folder 18)
      - 1946-1957 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Song card file, A-D, 1938-1947 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Song card file, H-Ma, 1938-1949 and undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Song card file, Me-Si, 1938-1947 and undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Song card file, Sl-Z, 1938-1947 and undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Subseries 2: Decca Records, 1936-1982, undated
    Arranged alphabetically by artist name or folder title.
    - Artist Files
      - Allan, Lewis, 1950-1959 (Box 2, Folder 4)
      - Andrews Sisters, 1949-1952, 1973-1974 (Box 2, Folder 5)
      - Arden, Toni, 1957-1959 (Box 2, Folder 6)
      - Armstrong, Louis, 1951-1970, undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
      - Barnet, Charlie, 1975, undated (Box 2, Folder 8)
      - Beiderbecke, Bix, undated (Box 2, Folder 9)
      - Brazen Brass, 1960-1973, undated (Box 2, Folder 10)
      - Brown, Les, 1958-1975, undated (Box 2, Folder 11)
      - Carmichael, Hoagy, 1957, undated (Box 2, Folder 12)
      - Condon, Eddie, 1944-1982 (Box 2, Folder 13)
      - Cooley, Spade, 1953, undated (Box 2, Folder 14)
      - Country / Western and Sacred / Gospel, undated (Box 2, Folder 15)
      - Crosby, Bing, 1956-1961, undated (Box 2, Folder 16)
      - Crosby, Bob, 1950-1975 (Box 2, Folder 17)
      - Cugat, Xavier, 1965-1975, undated (Box 2, Folder 18)
      - Curtain Calls, 1952-1962, undated (Box 2, Folder 19)
      - Davis, Sammy, 1956-1961, undated (Box 2, Folder 20)
      - Dee, Lenny, 1955-1968, undated (Box 2, Folder 21)
      - Do Re Mi, 1959-1973, undated (Box 2, Folder 22)
      - Dorsey, Jimmy, 1950-1975, undated (Box 2, Folder 23)
      - Dorsey, Tommy, 1950-1975, undated (Box 2, Folder 24)
      - Eldridge, Roy, undated (Box 2, Folder 25)
      - Feather, Leonard, 1969 (Box 2, Folder 26)
      - Fifty Years of Movie Music, 1960, undated (Box 2, Folder 27)
      - Fields, Irving, 1959, 1961 (Box 2, Folder 28)
      - Five Feet of Swing, 1951-1952, undated (Box 2, Folder 29)
      - Floren, Myron, 1959-1960, undated (Box 2, Folder 30)
      - Fountain, Pete, 1973, 1976, undated (Box 2, Folder 31)
      - Garber, Jan, 1958-1970 (Box 2, Folder 32)
      - Girl Trios, undated (Box 2, Folder 33)
      - Goodman, Benny, 1965-1966, undated (Box 2, Folder 34)
      - Grant, Earl, 1959-1976, undated (Box 2, Folder 35)
      - Gray, Glen, 1952-1975, undated (Box 2, Folder 36)
      - Haley, Bill, 1954-1982, undated (Box 2, Folder 37)
      - Hampton, Lionel, 1963-1965, undated (Box 2, Folder 38)
      - Haymes, Dick, 1950-1958, 1973, 1976, undated (Box 2, Folder 39)
      - Herman, Woody, 1948-1975, undated (Box 2, Folder 40)
      - Hibbler, Al, 1956-1975, undated (Box 2, Folder 41)
      - Holiday, Billie, 1959-1976, undated (Box 2, Folder 42)
      - Holly, Buddy, 1965, 1970, undated (Box 2, Folder 43)
      - Houdini, Wilmoth, 1973, undated (Box 2, Folder 44)
      - Ives, Burl, 1953-1966, undated (Box 2, Folder 45)
      - Jesus Christ Superstar, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 46)
      - Johnson, Buddy, 1941-1973, undated (Box 2, Folder 47)
      - Jordan, Louis, 1942-1975, undated (Box 2, Folder 48)
      - Kaempfert, Bert
        General note
        File includes 6-inch 45 RPM acetate, Harry Middlebrooks “It Makes No Difference” and 6-inch 45 RPM, Bert Kaempfert and His Orchestra “The Little Drummer Boy”/”Jingo Jango"
        - 1966-1974, undated (Box 3, Folder 1)
        - Hamburg lyrics, 1969-1970 (Box 3, Folder 2)
        - Music from the film, "A Man Could Get Killed", 1966 (Box 3, Folder 3)
      - Kaye, Sammy, 1960-1970 (Box 3, Folder 4)
      - King, Wayne, 1955-1970, undated (Box 3, Folder 5)
      - Kirk, Andy, 1936-1954, 1975-1976, undated (Box 3, Folder 6)
      - Latin music (Machito, Miguelito Valdes, Noro Morales, Esy Morales, Quarteto Caney), 1964, undated (Box 3, Folder 7)
      - Lawson-Haggart, 1958-1963, undated (Box 3, Folder 8)
      - Lee, Peggy, 1955-1963, undated (Box 3, Folder 9)
      - Lewis, Ted, 1956, 1976, undated (Box 3, Folder 10)
      - Lombardo, Guy, 1954-1975, undated (Box 3, Folder 11)
      - Maize, Joe, undated (Box 3, Folder 12)
      - Marches, 1951-1967, undated (Box 3, Folder 13)
      - Martin, Freddy, 1967, 1975, undated (Box 3, Folder 14)
      - McCall, Mary Ann, 1959 (Box 3, Folder 15)
      - McGuire Sisters, 1957-1966, undated (Box 3, Folder 16)
      - Mendez, Rafael, 1956-1976, undated (Box 3, Folder 17)
      - Millinder, Lucky, 1942-1947, undated (Box 3, Folder 18)
      - The Modernaires, 1957-1958, undated (Box 3, Folder 19)
      - Mooney, Art, 1961 (Box 3, Folder 20)
      - Morgan, Russ, 1950-1974, undated (Box 3, Folder 21)
      - Polkas, 1959-1968, undated (Box 3, Folder 22)
      - Ray Charles Singers, 1958-1966 (Box 3, Folder 23)
      - Record personnel sheets, Decca Records, 1944-1958 (Box 3, Folder 24)
      - Russell, George, 1960-1961, 1971, undated (Box 3, Folder 25)
      - Scott, Little Jimmy, 1969, undated (Box 3, Folder 26)
      - Shaw, Artie, 1950-1956, 1975, undated (Box 3, Folder 27)
      - Smith, Ethel, 1955-1969, 1976, undated (Box 3, Folder 28)
      - Southern, Jeri, 1954-1966 (Box 3, Folder 29)
      - Spanier, Muggsy, 1944-1954, undated (Box 3, Folder 30)
      - Square dance, 1959, undated (Box 3, Folder 31)
      - Tharpe, Sister Rosetta, 1951, 1958, undated (Box 3, Folder 32)
      - Valentino Tangos, 1953-1976, undated (Box 3, Folder 33)
      - Viennese waltzes, 1950-1959 (Box 3, Folder 34)
      - Waring, Fred, 1964-1976, undated (Box 3, Folder 35)
      - Webb, Chick, 1967-1976, undated (Box 3, Folder 36)
      - Welk, Lawrence, 1955-1969, undated (Box 3, Folder 37)
      - Williams, Roger, 1966-1971, undated (Box 3, Folder 38)
    - Brunswick albums
      - 1946 (Box 3, Folder 39)
      - Master index, 1946 (Box 3, Folder 40)
      - Master record list, 1947 (Box 3, Folder 41)
    - Decca Numerical Catalog
      - circa 1940s (Box 3, Folder 42)
      - circa 1950 (Box 3, Folder 43)
    - Jazz data and albums, 1945 (Box 3, Folder 44)
    - Memoranda regarding disc jockeys, 1960 (Box 3, Folder 45)
  - Subseries 3: Lyrics and Sheet Music, 1940-1970, undated
    Arranged alphabetically by title, with miscellaneous lyrics and fragments at the end.
    - A-D, 1945-1968, undated (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - E-L, 1940-1969, undated (Box 4, Folder 2)
      Includes 6-inch 45 RPM acetate recording of “Lovely”
    - M-R, 1947-1967, undated (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - S-T, 1949-1970, undated (Box 4, Folder 4)
      Includes 10-inch 45 RPM EP of “Since I Fell in Love with You” and 10-inch 45 RPM acetate recording of “Steppin’ Pretty”
    - U-Z, 1949-1967, undated (Box 4, Folder 5)
      Includes 6-inch 45 RPM recording of “Unbelievable”
    - Miscellaneous handwritten lyrics and song fragments, undated (Box 4, Folder 6)
- Series II: Personal Files, 1938-2000
  Series II: Personal Files contains miscellaneous papers not directly attributable to Gabler’s work at Commodore and Decca Records, including awards, clippings, a Duke Ellington concert program, correspondence, the contents of an index card file, memoranda and notes, and radio transcripts. The folders are organized by type and then chronologically.
  - Awards
    - National Academy of Recording Arts and Sciences (NARAS), 1974-1984, 1995 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - National Academy of Recording Arts & Sciences (NARAS) President’s Merit Award, 1995 (Box OS1, Object 1)
    - NARAS Hall of Fame Award for Lionel Hampton’s “Flying Home”, 1996 (Box OS1, Object 2)
    - Songwriters’ Hall of Fame, 2000 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Clippings
    - Articles by Ralph Gleason and Gleason obituary, 1958, 1971-1975 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Guthrie, Woody, 1967 (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - “A Lady Named Billie And I” Downbeat, 1973 March 29, undated (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - Wellstood, Dick, 1976, undated (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Duke Ellington and His Famous Orchestra, Fifth Annual New Year’s Concert (concert program), 1939 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence
    - Goldfarb, Herman, 1965, undated (Box 4, Folder 14)
    - Jolson-Krasna, Erle, 1962-1969 (Box 4, Folder 15)
    - Lomax Records, 1939 (Box 4, Folder 16)
    - Miscellaneous, 1933-1945, 1966, 1987, 1994 (Box 4, Folder 17)
    - Weinstein, Bob, 1985, 1989 (Box 4, Folder 18)
      Letter was originally found in John Hammond: On Record: An Autobiography.
  - Index card file, undated
  - Interview transcripts
    - Milt Gabler, interviewed by Ralph Gleason, 1974 (Box 4, Folder 19)
    - Milt Gabler, Oral History Research Office, Columbia University, 1959 (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Memoranda and notes, miscellaneous, undated (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - Radio transcripts
    - The Benny Goodman Show, 1941 April 21 (Box 4, Folder 22)
    - Dr. Jazz, with accompanying fan mail, 1938 (Box 4, Folder 23)
    - Jam Session, circa 1940s (Box 4, Folder 24-25)
- Series III: Printed Materials, 1949-1995
  Series III: Printed Materials is arranged by format and then alphabetically by title.
  Separated Materials
  Many publications have been transferred to the library collection. Please search for the "Milt Gabler Collection" in the library catalog for a list of donated titles.
  - Bound Periodicals
    - DownBeat yearbook, 1942 (Box OS2, Object 1)
    - DownBeat yearbook, 1943 (Box OS2, Object 2)
    - DownBeat yearbook, 1944 (Box OS2, Object 3)
  - Newspapers
    - Daily News (New York), 1977 July 15 (Box OS1, Object 3)
    - Daily News (New York), 1977 August 12 (Box OS1, Object 4)
    - New York Post, 1977 July 15 (Box OS1, Object 5)
    - New York Post, 1977 August 12 (Box OS1, Object 6)
  - Programs
    - The Grammy Winners Book, 36th Annual Grammy Awards, 1994 (Box 5, Object 1)
    - National Academy of Recording Arts & Sciences (NARAS) ceremony honoring James B. Conkling, 1995 (Box 5, Object 2)
    - World Championship of Jazz, 1975 (Box 5, Object 3)
  - Sheet music
    - Dixieland New Orleans Folio No. 1, Melrose Music Corp., 1950 (Box 5, Object 4)
    - Dixieland New Orleans Folio No. 2, Melrose Music Corp., 1950 (Box 5, Object 5)
    - Dixieland New Orleans Folio No. 3, Melrose Music Corp., 1950 (Box 5, Object 6)
    - Jelly Roll Morton’s Folio, Melrose Music Corp., 1949 (Box 5, Object 7)
    - Miscellaneous, 1949-1962 (Box 5, Folder 1)
- Series IV: 1/4-inch Audiotapes [RESTRICTED], 1937-1986, undated
  Series IV: 1/4-Inch Audiotapes is arranged alphabetically by title and then chronologically.
  Ten-inch LP, 78 rpm, 78 rpm sets, 45 rpm, 45 rpm EP, and LP records have been transferred to the library collection. Please search for the "Milt Gabler Collection" in the library catalog for a list of donated titles.
  Access Restrictions
  The 1/4-inch audiotapes in this series are on defunct media and, therefore, are RESTRICTED. Access copies of these materials will have to be created prior to use. Consult the Library and Archives staff in advance of your visit to ensure access to these materials is available.
  - Bill Culter Tribute to Commodore Music Shop and Milt Gabler, 1960 November 27 (Box 5, Reel 1)
  - George Barber Show, Greenwich CT -- "program tapes of our show", undated (Box 5, Reel 2-3)
  - WBT Charlotte, NC. Radio show "Milt Gabler - Starmaker", 1965 August (Box 5, Reel 4-5)
  - WVOX Milt Gabler - Bert Kaempfert, 1981 September 18 (Box 5, Reel 6-7)
  - WVOX Milt Gabler – Harry Warren, 1981 September 25 (Box 5, Reel 8-9)
  - WVOX Milt Gabler – Victor Young, 1981 October 9 (Box 5, Reel 10)
  - WVOX Milt Gabler- Jack Pleis, 1981 October 16 (Box 5, Reel 11)